so I wanted to ask about mindful czar
green and how that should be done we can
read these the suit over and over again
try and follow some sort of method step
by step we then read out what are you
thinking about my body I think this
happened do that I do this I do that and
you can go you can actually run through
all their steps forwards backwards
whatever you want I still don't do the
mindfulness of breathing yes well as the
name itself says it's that it's
mindfulness mindfulness of breathing so
in order to the mindfulness of breathing
you need to know what mindfulness is
yeah so mindfulness as we spoke in other
in other talks if mindfulness is not
rightly it's effortless so mindfulness
is not something you can do
mindful is something you discern on
account active presently enduring things
experiences the whole feelings body any
there are many different ways you can
establish mindfulness but principle of
mindfulness is the same to be discerned
so what is it that you discerned in
order to become mindful well you for
example you discern your present
enduring situation so you have an option
you can be absorbed with the presently
enduring situation something can take
away hundred percent of your attention
you're dealing with this problem you're
looking at this or doing that but
including self awareness into whatever
you're doing that's already like a step
closer to the proper mindfulness and
there's not something you can do it's
more like an attitude that you can have
in regard to things you do that's what
fundamentally your meditation method is
inherently wrong from the point of view
of mindfulness because you can't be
doing the mindfulness yet as the Buddha
said station is nothing other than unshakable
station is nothing other than unshakable
imperturbable establishment of
mindfulness so if you're not doing
mindfulness from the start how can you
magically establish it through something
you do some methods or repetitions so
it's a recognition of your situation
while at the same time simultaneously
without recognition you are in the
situation in other words I'm sitting on
the chair now and we like a corner of
your eye with the back of your mind you
are aware of that that doesn't mean I
need to stand up or lay down or start
walking in order to know that I was
seated on the chair that's why the
fundamental like the bodily postures or
just awareness of the body so my phone
is up probably means basically awareness
of your situation beat-beat but it is
kind of established upon the body or
feelings or the states of mind the moods
means it's established in that
background so you're not attending it
I'm not I don't have to keep sitting in
I'm seated I'm seated I'm seated I don't
need to keep repeating it to myself why
because I already know that I'm seated
even if I don't think about it so if you
were to ask me what's your body push are
meters I'm seated and that's what you
want to tap into so to speak proper
development of mindfulness is tapping
into what you already know
it's not doing what you think you must
be doing oh I'm seeing I'm seeing I'm
feeling the chair I'm feeling the chair
my back my my legs a folder I feel in
the Florida that's all result of you
already knowing that you are seated
that's not just sitting in other words
whether you're attending to your feet
and your back and whatever else going on
while you're seated that's secondary to
the fact that you are already seated and
you already know that so instead of like
giving in to that all I'm doing this I'm
doing this almost like basically
exercising your sense of control over
over your meditation technique you want
to recognize it wait a minute Howard
didn't know what I'm doing and then just
try not to forget that little bit that
1% that one grain don't forget what you
already know which means you don't need
active effort of reminding yourself that
you see today you seated in your seated
all you need to do is just keep a corner
of your on the fact that you already
know that you're seated and how do you
know because you
seated so that knowledge doesn't come
from you you just set a cognition of how
things are that's why through that
mindfulness you can learn how to discern
how things are
that's why that type of mindfulness will
result in discerning impermanence
suffering lack of control all of that
but if one is not if you do it on your
own terms which is this is what I'm
doing this my meditation of touching
touching feeling feeling sitting sitting
that's you basically doing what you
think you should be doing but the fact
is Patricia already starts with the
wrong view which means whatever he
thinks he should be doing he will be
doing it with the wrong view that's why
you can't have too much room mindfulness
Ida cuz it's not doing is the recognition of
cuz it's not doing is the recognition of
what you already know and that knowledge
is not a new same we have got two body
postures or in regards to the presently
enduring feeling again that's something
you already know so if I ask you how do
you feel you might think about how you
feel in this particularly not happening
but if I ask you how'd you feel overall
is it okay because your mood generally
you'll immediately know whether it's
sort of plus or minus so it's big
whether it's okay whether it isn't okay
whether it's neither
so it's tapping into what you already
know and you already know it because
it's present on its own terms
feeling is there a during which ever it
is and it's because of you not keeping a
corner of your eye on what you already
know that's why you get sort of
distracted pull with sensuality ill-will
reacting causing more trouble for
yourself all these things that's what
people are afraid to be alone as well
because they depend on something to take
away their attention to have something
to attend to included a meditation
technique with this so this to this and
they don't stay with what they already
know because it's it's frightening
initially at least if you were to just
not do anything including your
meditation technique like the pressure
is gonna start building up solitude not
doing anything like doing is required
for the maintenance of your being that
so many people depend on activity of all
sorts yeah you have a good activity bad
activity bear activity but overall you depend on
bear activity but overall you depend on
the activity so mindfulness is not an
activity that's why you can't have too
much of it and that's why you can
actually develop wisdom on account of it
if you start is earning it right and
that's why you need to know what
mindfulness is in order to do it rightly
know just like a mindful now yeah you
can't stay you can't start perfectly you
can't start rightly from the beginning
but you can certainly arrive at it if
you don't take for granted but you think
mindfulness is as mindfulness look if I
were to know what mindfulness is I would
have at least the right to view I would
be at least a sorta banner see if I'm
not sober means I don't quite know what
mindfulness is so whatever I think
mindfulness is I must upgrade through
that I must discern it further either
way it's a win-win if you already know
what mindfulness is great doing more of
it cannot bring any harm if you don't
know what mindfulness is and then you
end up doing more and you understand
what mindfulness is you win again so
nothing to lose by regarding yourself as
not knowing quite what mindfulness is
and because of that pushing further well
the only thing you have to lose is your
vanity and conceit they made you believe
you already understood and know and they
already helpful and in ordered it works
because if it does you wouldn't have a
problem upgrading it or pushing it
further because if it truly works it
will standard test nothing will happen
to it but the fact that some people
might be defending their meditation
technique or something and get very
touchy over it or over their practice of
mindfulness means is basically is
passion invested in literally there's
conceit and vanity invested in it and
that's on mindfulness then so now that
we clarify what mindfulness is
mindfulness of breathing so you you can
do the breathing but you can't do the
mindfulness in mindfulness of breathing
so in other words saying mindfulness of
breathing means knowledge of breathing
knowledge of the act of breathing and
that's why the Buddha says in its with
the knowingly he breathing knowingly
every job that's what his mindfulness is
it's at that level of the discern
of what's already there so in other
words you can be mindful of the body
posture or you want to be mindful of
something less static let's put it that
way you would have be mindful of of an
activity or something you do so what is
the neutral activity that your body does
whether you want it or not
it's breathing in breathing out so you
want to be aware of the background of
your act of breathing in and breathing
out in other words you don't be
attending to your breath in it directly
you want to make it sort of become a
background of whatever your minds
thinking it's you're mindful of
breathing oh you can you can even bring
it to the foreground if you want but
again not in a sense of I'm perceiving
my breath and B our nostrils also know
it still has to be on the level of that
knowledge because if I ask you now are
you breathing you will know that you are
and you don't have to stop reading in
order to give me the answer no you need
to wait a minute you can't even doubt it
so you don't have to stop breathing to
give me the answer you can't even doubt
whether you're breathing or not so you
already know that you're breathing so
that's what you want to learn through
the mindfulness of breathing a
recognition of what you already know and
that's not something you always have to
maintain or even can maintain 100% if
I'm breathing completely now let it let
it drift away without losing the sight
of it so here here I am sitting semi
comfortably not too comfortably because
you fall asleep why the way guys open
and you're breathing and now you know
that you know that you are breathing
that's it
what do I do next nothing you do that so
there is Dean breath there is the
out-breath there is the in-breath there is the
there is the in-breath there is the
out-breath either way they all stand
within that knowledge of I am reading
whether it's a particular in breath or
particular the knowledge of breathing
remains the same that's why then the
Buddha would say you would breathe in
like this or like this or short breath a
long breath or like this
like that breath point being the
knowledge of that breeding still stays
the same
mindfulness gets established regardless
of the type of breath or how different
it is and it's the same principle
mindfulness is simply like the mindful
of the body but the Buddha would say is
mindful to the body ladies Michael
standing Oh
he's mindful to the extent necessary for
final knowledge that body is there as in
the ultimate background of any of your
activity is the background of your body
being present there is a basis on on
account of which you can do all these
activities and engagements feel feelings
perceive receptions and so on so if your
mind never forgets that 0.01% what it
already knows of that body being a
necessary basis for it your mind cannot
give rise to a video whether you
recognize it at that time or not doesn't
matter you're doing it rightly if you're
doing it right Lee the time will come
when you've done it rightly sufficiently
did you recognize what you've been doing
rightly that's also another reason why
nobody can accidentally stumble upon the
right view it takes repetition
repetition repetition of something you
took I did through like intellectual
discernment or on faith but you've been
doing it rightly you doing running
sufficiently then you recognize right as right which
then you recognize right as right which
is the basic definition of sotapanna
he knows who Salah is Kosala and
Cousteau as acasola but he would have
narrated it if you haven't been doing it
rightly on account of utterance of
another and his own faith in it and
likely understanding it and then
intellectual level so mindfulness of
breathing same principle of mindfulness
breathing is there whether it's a short
breath long breath quick breath slow
breath breathing is there and that's
what you know so in the way breathing is
doing but knowledge of the breathing is
not doing so why would the Buddha then
say doing because yeah sometimes you
want to do something you want to replace
course doing with refine doing you want
to replace unwholesome doing with
wholesome doing and breathing being the
most neutral type of doing is the
wholesome is doing you can do because
it's just neutral doesn't harm anyone
doesn't harm you
so you can develop mindfulness you can
develop knowledge of that neutral type
of doing and it's also repetitive doing
which means it doesn't require your
attention as if like solving a task or
doing some like menial work or whatever
no it's just breathing it happens
whether you think about it or not
so you want to discern it on the level
of doing but discern it know do it
yourself so how do you do that
stop breathing secluded alone ask
yourself am i breathing right now
yes that's already like a an increment
of that right direction of that
knowledge so you already know your
breathing are you still breathing yes
so you still know your breathing still
the same ready same knowledge yeah so
you have same thing enduring now now you
don't even have to go as to ask yourself
whether you're breathing you just remind
yourself what you already know yeah you
are still breathing so you can stop
saying you can stop saying still you can
just say yeah I'm breathing don't you
have to say you can think it when you
become familiar with that as in right
now I'm still breathing you can then
look within that oh the breath is quite
slow right now and you already know that
you're not doing it you're discerning it
what's being done well you can do it but
you realize that you yourself doing it
is secondary to discernment of what's
being done and that's incidentally I
also have come the nature of action how
you disown it but let's not complicate
things here are you still breathing you
are all this time you had the same
all this time you had the same
mindfulness of the same craving yeah
particularly the breath kept going in
kept going out overall breathing is
there body sits body stands up all the
girl's body lays down body's there
that's one upon a sati results in the
four foundations of mindfulness being
brought to fulfillment as the Buddha
said doesn't result in mystical
experiences of of meditating lights and
what not results in clarity of
mindfulness clarity of mindfulness
results in the forest strivings forests
ravines in noble and enlightening
factors that's it no other work for you
to be done
why because you brought that knowledge
of the nature of things to fulfillment
to the fall well yeah so like bringing
mindfulness of breathing to the four
means okay am i breathing now okay am I
still aware that I am reading now yes
how am I really now
medium pace you can call it you can
designate there is no right answer to it
there's only right direction of wrong
direction as in there's only knowledge
of it or no knowledge oh it
oh by the way how am I feeling while I'm
reading right now fundamentally Pleasant
why am I still breathing yeah so
mindfulness is still concerned but the
lack of a better word anchored for the
lack of a better word in the act of
reading what are the thoughts that keep
popping up in my mind while I'm reading
same breathing say mindfulness same
knowledge of the same training well
their thoughts maybe I'm thinking how
long can I do this or what do I do next
okay so at those Patil's Pleasant or not
present while I'm reading this I didn't
stop reading voila thinking all of this
it's just I haven't lost the sight as
the basis of all these things well I'm
feeling maybe like doubtful or whatever
people might feel whatever you
discovered as I said there is no right
answer there is only losing the sight of
your breathing or non losing the sight
of the bleeding then whatever mind stop
thinking about it what is the state of
my mind while I'm breathing this am I
depressed am i elated am I happy am i
sad what is my mood while I'm breathing
in breathing out all this time and there
you go anything else mr. barrini just
keep doing that cuz you'll be developing
mindfulness of body mindfulness of
feelings mindfulness of the mind in
mindfulness of the thoughts which is
satavahanas which is why I had
appendicitis of the sense that
fulfillment of annapurna SOT he brings
the fulfillment of sati patatas nothing
else
it also says that you get rid of
distracting throw exactly because they
are all rooted in losing the sight of
that peripheral in losing mindfulness
basically not being anchored in the
recognition of what's peripherally in
during the background exactly that's
lost aversion that is a necessary basis
for lost diversion and distraction to
arise losing the sight of what you
already know that certain feelings body
tensions perceptions are enduring
they're on their own in their background
and you actively choose to ignore them
hence that's why everybody's fully
responsible for the greed aversion
delusion it's not accidental it's
maintained through your consciously
basically made decisions now that you
fully understand decisions you're making
but you are doing it you choose to go
down the sensuality you choose to go
down the oh well you choose to not say
no to those things including the
distraction that's what the one who
understands that all you need to do is
stop the lighting in it he doesn't stop
thinking sensual thoughts or bad
thoughts but he stopped delighting in
them that's how you stop thinking not by
preventing him from arising but by not
fueling them further and mindfulness of
breathing is let's see if you're just
mindful I'm seated I'm seated I'm seated
you're not doing anything so you you
know you can fall asleep or you could
get easily distracted but breathing is
something that's kind of done which
means it's more active yet at the same
time the principle of mindfulness is not
compromised because it doesn't really
take away your attention so the basis of
knowing that breathing is there you can
discern what kind of breathing is there
on the basis of knowing that breathing
is there you can discern what feelings
are there on the basis of knowing the
breathing is there you can discern what
mood is there on the basis of knowing
what breathing is there you can discern
what exactly is your mind thinking right
now particular thought to this those are
their thoughts so the basis of doing
things your discerning what's present
you develop that that means even less
and less chances of being distracted
even when you are not practicing
actively whatever any meditation where
you're sweeping leaves going walking
sitting extending dead mindfulness
pertains to it because again you don't
necessarily to think I'm breathing I'm
breathing and breathing you already know
you're breathing so you just learn
basically how to tap into that point of
view of that breathing being already
there of that body being already there
which automatically is something that is
not your point of view because you are
not doing it
so it comes before you appointed yeah
well it becomes before your
appropriation of the point of view
through action as you know I'm looking
at this I'm doing this that's my point
of view but the only way you can do only
reason you're able to do that is because
these things are there on their own
enduring already bodies their feelings
and their perceptions are their
intentions are they're pretty much
so again also all these two there are no
steps to mindfulness really there is
mindfulness of reading and different
aspects of it of the same principle of
mindfulness of breathing I'm breathing
I'm still breathing still the same
mindful is that all this time since
we've been talking about it yeah lots of
things have changed in a particularly
new thoughts new moods new feelings yet
that breathing is still the same
mindfulness knowledge of that same
breathing is still there that annette
reading is the nutriment it's its basis
it's like a reference point it's an
anchor it's a background basically of
everything else more particular
they want to see that that's eventually
at least well there is no endgame there
is no like and then this happens if you
just keep doing that what's going to
happen is everything in failure to it
everything more particular to it it's
going to be purified of greed aversion
delusion he's going to be purified of
the basis of non mindfulness why because
you're developing bases of mindfulness
so you're moving through doing it you're
removing the nutriment for all the
unwholesome things you've been doing and
deciding to do mindfulness of breathing
is on the level of mindfulness of death
or any other mindfulness that's where
the Buddha thought it as a replacement
to murder and a sati he said now okay
instead of that because some monks can't
quite handle it practice this but it's
the same goal as in stick basically with
the most fundamental discernment of
things not being your control being
already they're enduring despite whether
you want them or not whether you do them
or not it is a death of your sense of
self death of your activity you'd you
are the one who maintains the muon who
is in control that sense just gets
completely pushed out to fades away so
you ready to mind sense of death how is
that done what ways the death you're
mindful of well I get my start with
mindfulness of the body you start seeing
the body it isn't necessary organic
literally made out of organs think in
the world they're because of which you
experience the world and everything else
in it all your happiness and sadness and
choices and decisions are inconceivable
if the body is still not there
simultaneously present in living do you
have any saying that that body did you
find it that you were given certain
height certain complexion whatever can
you make it knowledge can you prevent it
from getting sick can you ultimately
command it to never die
so those are the first three basic
things that people don't dwell on that's
what we'll say people are intoxicated
with life intoxicated with youth
intoxicated with health you use choose
to become intoxicated by refusing to
look at the obvious characteristics of
it because they are unpleasant they fill
you with anxiety so that inevitable
possibility of death yeah so once you
start recognizing the presence of the
body it's just a necessary nutriment for
the urban experience as a whole of any
kind you stop being concerned with the
particulars of that experience all this
bothers me this makes me happy you
realize it's fundamental nature is
undermined by the gratuitous presence of
the living body and when that changes
none of it can remain standing a second
longer none of your feelings or things
can stay so how can then then be yours
and that's basically beginning to
acknowledge death as in the destruction
that is an impending upon the body upon
the senses decay fading away this
integration you think about that you're
going to be less and less intoxicated
with things they come through it with
your sight sound smell taste are just
thoughts what because you recognize what
whatever they are they cannot step
outside of the confinement of the basis
necessary basis of this living body say
am i breathing yes while I'm breathing
what positions our body is in it's
heated that's heated body while I'm
breathing in and out right now what are
its characteristics just describe it in
any terms to yourself the most obvious
one it's just there isn't it it's living
it's just there
do you have seen any of those
characteristics can you change them can
you tell them to be otherwise so while
while I'm bleeding and my body is seated
while I'm breathing that body that I'm
discerning while I'm breathing in and
out while the breathing is there that
body them discerning through it it's
independent of me isn't it I can use it
but I cannot uphold it I cannot step
outside of it and on it
I cannot tell you what to do so it's
only borrowed which means everything
else that you get through the body is
equally borrowed and if something is
bothered is it the right thing for me to
regard it as mine and belonging to me
know if something is borrowed he's the
right thing for me to grieve and be sad
over it being taken away
no you require ignoring active ignoring
of the fact that you are not in control
in order to be to grieve over it to be
happy on it and smile phone is not
rightly results in discernment of the
natural principles which is what Dhamma
is nature nature of things you could see
how different that is from watching your
nostrils barely bobbing or whatever they
call it completely different I can't
doing this I'm feeling my belly rising
and falling rising and falling rising
and falling zero determined there you're
just trying to attend the momentary
presence of things hoping that somehow
it magically result in knowledge looking
for meaning results in knowledge tell me
the knife self-questioning self
interrogation all the things that we'll
talk about the suitors debts with the
results in the knowledge what about
watching someone die well with the right
attitude sure but not with not without
the right attitude okay watching someone
die and then seeing that your body your
living body right here right now is on
the level it's it's morally related it's
more related they're dying body tend to
your sense of ownership of that body
seen the same domain is the other dying
body's not in the domain of
you and this is my body that's how you
undermine your control your sense of
control you can't directly choose to not
control it or not own it but you can
undermine it
hence seeing that both is impermanent
because of that body cannot be the
reason for lasting satisfaction
automatically you experience that body
is not mine sabi sand garden each a
service Ankara touka-sama Tama Huata
so an independent origination assist
with birth aging intent yes so with this
life this manifestation of life and
that's what I see as a whole all that is
determined by or subject to fading away
subject to pending yes yeah but that
doesn't need to be your subject or you
don't need to be subjected to it
you are subjected to it because you have
appropriated you appropriated birth you
appropriately given body you
appropriated possibilities of the given
body in the census you appropriated it
by delighting in it by pursuing
pleasures that are secondary to it they
come on the basis of it you can't engage
in in sensual pleasure without
appropriation of the body it's
inconceivable so through engaging in sensual pleasure
so through engaging in sensual pleasure
you're responsible for your
appropriation of the body and then you
are liable to whatever that board is
liable to accidents aging death sickness
or it hence it's on you because you took
it through carelessly pursuing
sensuality yeah you stop regarding it is yours so
yeah you stop regarding it is yours so
your problem in in as much these raging
trees and other people's bodies are not
your problem because they are not yours
that's why they're not a problem it's
not they are not your problem
because there are other peoples they are
not a problem because other people you
never considered to be yours but
incidentally say if it's your son your
daughter your partner oh something that
you are emotional affective why because
it's mine so yeah you can appropriate
other people as well my friend and
that's why you suffer not because
they're dying you suffer because you
appropriated them and now you're feeling
that because you're liable to it so you
have a choice if you want to be free
from suffering you have to give up all
the appropriation if you don't want to
give a procreation that's absolutely
fine but then you make yourself liable
to suffering
but then again there is a contradiction
slight contradiction I think because if
you were then to be honest with yourself
and ask why don't I want to give up all
the preparations oh it's cause it's
unpleasant so you're still governed by the same
so you're still governed by the same
principle of wanting to avoid suffering
and that's why people protect their
attachments in appropriations because
they don't want to suffer ironically you
suffer because of that so if you were to
take the initial hit of suffering
ultimately you can free yourself from
suffering but if you are too weak to
take the initial hit of suffering you
make yourself liable to suffering
indefinitely either way everybody doesn't want to
either way everybody doesn't want to
suffer even people who say I want to
suffer they don't they want to suffer
because that provides in pleasure
because not getting that pleasure means
suffering that's why the bullying self
could have not taught anything different
than suffering and cessation of it
because that is at the root of every
universal in every human regardless of
the culture education identity and
whatnot that is always the basic principle avoid
that is always the basic principle avoid
pleasure avoid pain have pleasure not
having enough pleasure or getting more
pleasure means avoiding pain of not
having enough pleasure
and what do you think about the common
idea although you can say I'm not afraid
of death yeah well they're not afraid of
what they think death is which means
they don't know what that is because
only well only two people are not afraid
of death either fully enlighten our hunt
or fully deluded / - Jenna but one of
them is fully liable to death another
one is fully free from it but they both
are not afraid of it one is not afraid
you - the sheer amount of ignorance and
not even knowing what that is another
one is not afraid because you've
completely overcome it so unless you are
in our hunt you are afraid of death and
if you don't feel the fear it's because
you're covering it up don't think that
death is where you think death is think
the death is basically where you can't
get your pleasures when you can't get
usage of your senses well find the fears
you have in your life and death is at
the other end of them whatever those
fears particularly might be or which are
particular where they might have to
manifest whatever brings people anxiety
death is on the other side of that so if
you think I'm not afraid of that that
brings me no anxiety yeah cuz your idea
what that is is completely wrong but
something will be bringing anxiety and
that's where the death is so hands the
anxiety I'm afraid of losing all my
friends here you go death is at the
other end of that that's just a hint of
what death is Oh
losing it all
oh simply losing things that I do to me
or even more simplistically said being
disjoint from the agreeable being
separated from the agreeable being
United with disagreeable that's what
suffering is an ultimate suffering his
death
I'm not afraid of lying but I'm afraid
of what people think about me there you
go
death is basically not having say you
know what people will think about you
ultimately that's the most frightening
thing isn't it
well those will fear that or I'm gonna
favor dying but I'm afraid of losing my
my wealth I'm afraid of losing my family
I'm very public speaking I'm afraid of
public speaking why is that because
literally you it's the ultimate
experience of non control you you have
control over your speaking we have zero
control or how people will take that
what will they say what will they think
so ultimately what is that fear of death
it's fear of the ultimate non control
and it's not incidental that one thing
or the other will have to be reminding
you of that because the whole human
experience is about covering the fact
that you are not in control covering the
fact that you are liable to die as in
inevitably liable to die
so all these things loss in public speed
whatever frightens people frightens them
because it's the ultimate reminder of
the ultimate cessation of their any
notion of control they might have so
when people say I'm not afraid of dying
is because death thought is in their
control and they said that's what dying
is so they're not afraid of it
everybody dies yeah but why are you
afraid of public speaking
everybody does speaking everybody speaks
yet here you are terrified of public
speaking why because you constantly looking away
why because you constantly looking away
from the fact that you are not in
control and when your counter
experiences that you cannot ignore the
fact that you're not in control
frightens the hell out of you and that's
what death is the ultimate cessation of
any ground for your notion of control
that yet you take to be the most
fundamental thing I am therefore things
are mine therefore I'm in control yeah
yeah
another is please in death through
seeing that correctly means not being
able to entertain the notion of control
means not being my own self not being
myself not belonging to me not
appropriation that's all another say if
I see that for myself for myself and
then he's gonna scare the hell out of it
yes that's what happen innocence is in
it so if today people are not scared
when they read about a nothing and in
any bother it's good thing I have a clue
what it is what it really is
so for Patricia and Ivana is closer to
her death is the one that he's ignoring
so - Gina - ignoring death actually
ignores possibility of Nibbana that's
why those people who came to the Buddha
the way the Buddha would lay it out on
them they couldn't ignore it and they
would fall on the ground in complete
anxious despair I have a mental
breakdown saying this will kill me this
will destroy me yeah because they still
don't relinquish that they still get
reuters to assume the priority of their
sense of I am despite the evidence
showing the contrary
so but I'm not giving up I am thus I
will be destroyed but if you hear the
teaching you realize that could enough
could have not been yours even if you
wanted it to and the only reason you are
regarding it is yours is because you
didn't know that it cannot be yours and
how do you find out it cannot be used
through practicing mindfulness correctly
and seeing it inseparable from the
necessary basis of things that cannot be
yours so twirling of the characteristics of
so twirling of the characteristics of
the necessity of the body twelve on the
characteristic of necessity of breathing
dwelling on independence of the
president during feeling present your
perceptions you had seen yourself
inseparable from it
it's basically remoulding reshaping
going against the grain and forcing
yourself to see that your own very self
depends upon the basis that cannot be
yourself because if it were so the body would not
because if it were so the body would not
age will not get sick it will not die if
it were so the feelings would not change
it will always be pleasant the way you
wanted you but yet the Buddha said well
if that's feeling is yours which one is
it why did why is why do you then
experience this pleasure he feeling is
yours you wouldn't if you're in control
so through reminding you something
you're not in control through practicing
the modern and assert it correctly you
get to undermine your sense of self
gradually and gradually and gradually so
you won't freak out and have a breakdown
although someone's dead that's what I
would have said well do mindfulness of
breathing instead because if done
wrongly result in the same principle
being greedy discerned then if you are
truly unafraid of death
he couldn't afraid of it you will not be
oblivious to what's happening like some
sort of robot who doesn't cool off
significance of things no still your
friend dying but normal of the extent of
that experience perception and feeling
in regard to it can sort of overturn
your mind and make you think it's yours
that which it isn't
or that it's permanent that which it
isn't the only really the only attitude
you could possibly have is how could it
be otherwise how can something exactly
how can something that's been born and
grown no die is just like you well it's
actually insanity to think that to think
otherwise so grieving over death it sits on the
so grieving over death it sits on the
level of insanity because it's the most
like it's inconceivable so for somebody
who understood the nature of death to
think yeah but he falling is just it
doesn't apply how can it be otherwise
but you have to get used to this you
know if you can't you can't start doing
this while you may be difficulty while
you're dying oh good luck with that if
you ever done it while you were alive if
you haven't uncovered up the nature of
of death while you were alive you're not
gonna do it when you're tired it's too
late so you want to start facing it as
soon as you can
that's why basically understanding of
death understanding of the ultimate non
control means ultimately giving things
up relinquishing appropriation
relinquish assumption that's why
understanding of that fully means
Nibbana that's where so DiBona
who understood the nature of Nibbana or
arias our work in general often is said
in soda or if he doesn't obtain it
during the life he attains it at when he
is dying why cuz it's that's where he
comes from comes from the direction of
dying and cessation of control he's
understanding now he got careless and
lazy during the lifetime he hasn't been
making effort but death will force him
in the direction that he already
understood so that's why sometimes
somebody can become an arahant where the
right view at the moment of dying it's
not so mystical light that appears
before you die if the direction you
understood through your right view and
everything else and now you're forced
now you're dragged there and you already
understood it so you basically were
dragged there where you should have gone
while you were still alive but it's
still good to understand it but it's
even better to do it and not wait to be
dragged there even Ferrari esophagus
so are you still breathing now I'm
asking you are you breathing now yes so
is the experience of the breathing still
the same experience of the breathing yeah
yeah
how can you be all of us unless you get
another body so while you're breathing
right here and while we're talking while
you're breathing what is the general
what's your mood how are you feeling
overall yeah okay could be better could
be better while you're breathing in an
art
what's the pace of your breath did you
discern being done water breathing yeah
sure shallow but restricted restricted
all those things basically are just
maintaining the mindfulness of breathing
keeping you sort of all these questions
but if you do it properly long enough
you can stop asking questions because
you already know so then we'll come down
to its being brief it's being the
breathing in he's being done shallowly
shallowly I'm breathing in what's the
experience of what are they worth what
feelings am i experiencing while I'm
breathing shallowly in and out again
you're not doing it or finding the
answer you're just discerning what's
already there why because the feeling is
already there
the body is already there the mind is
already there the thoughts are already
there now you're just discerning them
through the basis of act of breathing
and why is that a good thing because
usually you discern these things or
experiences through the basis of my
sense of self but now you're doing
through the basis that is not your sense
of self so it makes you understand
eventually that you'll send ourselves
completely redundant whether you choose
to do things or not and that's what I
said that feeling that's discerned while
doing mindfulness of breathing is
feeling about feelings and it's develops
mindfulness of feelings but that's a
body among bodies as in your thoughts of
your body position while you're
breathing it's basically where your body
is there so seeing it in that
non-appropriated sense because you're
discerning it on the level of
non-appropriated breathing but if you
just my body's teeth I'm seated I'm
seated that's like you already lost any
right principle of mindfulness and your
full appropriate because you're
discerning your body being seated you're
discerning you like while you're
breathing I'm seated
while I'm breathing in deep slow breaths
I am seated but I have intention of
getting up you're not doing it you're
discerning it that's the difference
between done rightly or wrongly the
direction whether you're doing it or
whether you actually not doing it but
discerning it what's being done whether
you're establishing your Ponyo sense
yourself as in doing it as a method of
technique or you're undermining your
sense of self by seeing it stand
independently of me including the
present enduring feeling the intentions
of the thoughts you discern them which
means they're already there whether you
want them or not makes no difference
and it's that developing clarity in
regard to that know whether I want it or
not this is a reason because of that
it's impermanent everything I want to
note is secondary to it
thus you stop until you lose that that
that gratuitous priority that's assumed
to me doing it me wanting in my sense of
self and you don't have time breathing
I'm breathing like now again
I'm Sabrina it's the same breath that
you had five minutes ago and I asked you
the question the same experience of
breeding many different in in our
breaths but they individually are not
your concern
your concern is overall experience of
breathing the you still mindful as a
basis that's it so through that you can
discern further or not it's up to you
but not built further or not through
some technique or method or step1 step2
but they said what's already there or
like again ask yourself a question so
I'm agreeing right here right now while
I'm seating this room do you a man to
say yes cuz you already know you are
because you're thinking about it now
what are the characteristics of that
experience of breathing
don't ask to give the answer how's the
question and then allow your mom to do
it without jumping in the first answer
that pleases you so what's the
characteristic of your overall
experience of reading how would you
describe it no no right answer no wrong
answers how would you describe it
you let that endure can you be breathing
without the notion of the body implicit
in it possible inconceivable it's an
active thing it's an active thing sure
being done it's done on the basis of the
body so what is more necessary for the
breathing presence of the living body
and working lungs are you thinking about
it you're doing it which is more
fundamental it's the function in lungs
and open the airway is basically it's a
necessary condition for my breathing can
it be alive if I don't breathe cause you
only can it be alive if my always get
blocked or lungs collapsing stop working
can I tell my lungs to not stop working
can I command them to be able to even
know how they work well I have some idea
theory from biology medicine but it just
happens to me basically dwelling on all
these characteristics while you're
breathing means just discerning just
keep keep hammering it in basically did
you can't own things even if you want
because even your sense of ownership is
because things are given their own their
own independent of you so realize all by
noting the fact that things are given
independent of you my lungs my Airways
the breathing the body that's how you
see ownership that's why you either own
or you either feel so from ownership you
can't have a view on both or this is the
ownership this isn't on auto-ship so I
choose this
require you to step outside of your
experience which is inconceivable so you
just have to keep dwelling on the nature
of the very breathing you're doing right
here right now and you're developing the
nature of non control the nature of
impermanence the nature of fundamental
unsatisfactory experience because that
kind of pleasure we get from things is
underlined by the sense of control enjoy
an accomplishment but you realize that's
our demand by the fact it your bodies
are yours senses are not yours no
pleasure that comes to your senses can
be yours doesn't mean you can't enjoy it
you can't but it's a big price to pay
for enjoying it
deafened there is suffering trap so
enjoying the pleasures of your eye you
get your head gets chopped off when they
die disappears when it fades away or
even you just are losing your sight of
it growing old in saying goes for any
sense all that that we talk about it's
base can be apparent if you know what
questions to ask rightly know jump in
answer and actually look at the
discerning aspect or just within you
sitting here breathing in shallowly
feeling so covers let's think about a
feeling while I'm reading in so I'm
still breathing in I mean I'm saying it
because it's for the camera really but
you have to say to yourself but ask
yourself internally am i breathing in
even before you answer it
you already know you're bringing in so
while you're reading in what feeling is
enduring there whatever it is Pleasant
unpleasant neutral doesn't matter
don't try to define just see which
category would fit most accurately
Pleasant I suppose so what would be the
characteristics of that pleasure feeling
discern on the basis for me breathing
right here right now see I'm still
breathing I can you choose to breathe in
long and slow deep and shallow whatever
I can choose the bedroom how am I
feeling while I'm doing all that
nice Pleasant so what would you be
carried Nico that Pleasant feeling well
I discerned it as already being there
something is already there means you
haven't created it haven't you
you just found it so would it be a right
thing for you then to act upon that
feeling to want to prolong it to us make
it get rid of that becomes inconceivable
actually it's not a matter of choice so
to not being aware of the right nature
correct nature of the feeling you want
to get rid of it or prolong it or
distract yourself from it through being
aware of the right nature of that
feeling all these things becoming
conceivable side or or you can't be
aware of the both and then make your
choice as you know I see this and I see
this and I'm choosing to not do it means
you you you're not seeing it rightly
hence it's either alone or Pat alone as
the Buddha says either with the grain of
your senses of your craving or full of
the Evita or it's against it that's very
strength is absolutely necessary basis
without you because no matter of your
discernment if your body is speech are
not restrained and are still going with
the grain you are maintaining the
principle of ownership through then
drained reminder that suit services see
as the blind yes there you were already
blind I think that's what kind of right
well see basically see as though you
oddity relinquish your sight
yeah that's what it means doesn't mean
like pretend you're blind and you're not
seeing because what you're seeing was
never the problem he was you owning your
eyes and what it can come through them
that you were affected with everything
else that's experienced on account of it
so if you learn to like if you don't
forget the necessary basis for any site
you have are the physical organs of your
eyes that you are not in control they
will ultimately diminish and be
destroyed you cannot possibly then
assume that you really have desired
towards anything you see the necessary
basis for the desire toward sights is
using the site no pun intended losing
the perspective on the nature of the eye
that's necessary base for any sites so
ultimately you're gonna be blind when
you die you will be deaf when you die so
seeing the ultimate resolve death in
regard to your senses will will make you
overcome anything that comes to your
senses but it doesn't mean like you're
pretending you you're not seeing or
you're pretending which is what that the
wrong view said that the man who stole
but he said well I'm acting like I'm
blind and deaf as if I'm ignoring sights
and sounds I'm pretending I'm not seeing
you're not here and anybody say well
you're no better than that blind in a
deaf man that's something different
that's when people blame the sights and
sounds and any other senses for their
suffering failing to see that suffering
is applicable to them because they
appropriated the ownership of the senses
not because of what comes through them
so are you still breathing while we're
discussing this particular approach of
senses in eyes and blindness and
deafness yeah it's the same breath still
the same basis for mindfulness enduring
for like an hour now so we've been doing
mindfulness of breathing all this time
and discerning the Dharma within it all
the terms of the universal principles
not on your own terms or as accurately
as you could do whichever way you start
that's what like he looks at the sonic
signs and characteristics features of
this thing he doesn't like jump at the
answers that his mind provides am i
breathing yes more will be the
characteristics of his breathing
characteristics not like mechanical
description like my lungs are moving or
whatever that's that's irrelevant what
is the nature of this act of breathing
can I stop it when I want to hmm well
only relatively so can I make sure it
never goes away
do I have a sane vet which is necessary
for the active breathing the breathing
apparatus not the closest if an accident
were to happen a bacterial virus to
attack this organs would I still be able
to breathe less freely no so I'm taking
for granted did if we before ever there
will be in my control that will be
unobstructed why am i taking for granted
oh because I'm not thinking sufficiently
enough that I cannot take it for granted
that's it
what is the condition for ignorance it's
ignoring basically stop ignoring you
stop conditioning your ignorance stop
ignoring certain universal truths that's
it